<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<operatorModel
  xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator"
  xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
  	<context>
      <description>Buffer to support consistent regions.
Buffer can be used in a consistent region.  For each sequence in the consistent
region, it creates an ordered list of tuples.  As each tuple is received on its
input port, it copies the tuple to the list for the current sequence, then
forwards the tuple.  On reset, it replays the stored tuples from the
sequence to which it was reset.  When a checkpoint is retired, it discards
the list of tuples from the identified sequence, as well as any earlier
sequences it may still have.

Limitations
If this is used as an operator-driven start operator, it never initiates a drain.
If this is used in an autonomous region, its store of tuples will grow
continually until it fails.
When replaying tuples, the original order is preserved, but the time between
tuples is not.
Recommendations
This operator might be useful as a much lighter bridge from an autonomous
region to a consistent region.  It offers a lower assurance against data loss.
If a reset is needed because of a failure of any other operator in the
consistent region, the Buffer operator will be able to replay the tuples
from the failed sequence.  However, if the Buffer operator itself fails,
data will be lost.
</description>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Never</providesSingleThreadedContext>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
      <inputPortSet>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>OptionallyWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>WindowBound</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </inputPortSet>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortSet>
        <expressionMode>Nonexistent</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>true</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>true</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>false</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Preserving</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </outputPortSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
